Guide to the John Richardson Kilby papers, 1680-1919 and undated, bulk 1840-1889
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Richardson Kilby papers 1680-1919 and undated bulk 1840-1889
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kilby, John Richardson, 1819-1878.
14.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 39,509 Items
Kilby and his son, Wilbur John Kilby (1850-1907), were both lawyers of Suffolk, Virginia, and of members of the Riddick family. Correspondence and legal and other papers of Kilby and of his son, Wilbur John Kilby (1850-1907), both lawyers, of Suffolk, Va., and of members of the Riddick family. The bulk of the collection concerns such legal activities of the Kilbys as administration of estates, collection of bills, and adjustments of property. The collection is important in part for its early records of families and references to politics and social conditions of Nansemond County, Virginia, but also for its references to slavery, the American Colonization Society and conditions in Liberia, and for its slave lists from the Riddick and Glazebrook families. There are many wills, one of which refers to the manumission of slaves. Other items refer to the legal affairs of the Riddick family, Richard H. Riddick, merchant of Pantego, N.C., and agent of the Albemarle Swamp Land Company; pro-Civil War activities of the Methodist Episcopal Church; Southampton Insurrection of 1831; Civil War action near Shepherdstown and Fredericksburg; African American soldiers during Reconstruction; the Negro Reformatory Association of Virginia; the gold rush of Pike's Peak, Colorado; a Suffolk, Va. cholera epidemic; and the Panic of 1857.
RL.00806
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Richardson Kilby papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1942-1952.
Collection Overview
Correspondence and legal and other papers of Kilby and of his son, Wilbur John Kilby (1850-1907), both lawyers, of Suffolk, Virginia, and of members of the Riddick family. The bulk of the collection dates from 1840-1889 and concerns such legal activities of the Kilbys as administration of estates, collection of bills, and adjustments of property. The collection is important in part for its records of families and social conditions of Nansemond County, Virginia.
Other important subjects include genealogical information for other families; the case of Harriet Whitehead, whose mind was impaired by the loss of her family in the Nat Turner Southampton Insurrection, 1831; freedom for slaves, with references to the work of the American Colonization Society and to life and conditions in Liberia; legal affairs of the Riddick family, Richard H. Riddick, merchant of Pantego, N.C., and agent of the Albemarle Swamp Land Company; pro-Civil War activities of the Methodist Episcopal Church; the Suffolk, Va. cholera epidemic (1849); the Panic of 1857 and the Pike's Peak, Colorado gold rush in 1859; action around Fredericksburg and Shepherdstown during the Civil War; African American soldiers in Charleston, S.C. during Reconstruction; Nansemond County, Virginia politics, especially during W. J. Kilby's career; and the Negro Reformatory Association of Virginia.
Several slave lists date from 1839-1858. The most extensive is of the Riddick family in undated legal papers. As the Office of Clerk of County burned in 1866, the legal, financial, and genealogical records are valuable for their information. A partial list of wills also exists, including the wills of Josiah Riddick, Richard Riddick, and John Glazebrook. One will, later contested, stipulates the manumission of a slave. Volumes include daybooks, memoranda, account books, notebooks, both professional and personal, as well as broadsides of land sales in Nansemond County, Virginia. The genealogical records are a photocopy of the printed genealogy of the Kilby, Jynes, Riddick, and Glazebrook families.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Kilby, Wilbur John, 1850-1907; Kilby family; Riddick, Richard H.; Albemarle Swamp Land Company; American Colonization Society; Methodist Episcopal Church -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Negro Reformatory Association of Virginia; African Americans -- Colonization -- Africa; Cholera -- Virginia -- Suffolk; Depressions -- 1857 -- Virginia; Lawyers -- Virginia -- Suffolk -- Correspondence; Merchants -- North Carolina -- Pantego; Probate law and practice -- Virginia; Reconstruction -- South Carolina -- African American troops; Southampton Insurrection, 1831; Charleston (S.C.) -- Social conditions; Colorado -- Gold discoveries; Fredericksburg (Va.) -- History -- 19th century; Nansemond County (Va.) -- Genealogy; Nansemond County (Va.) -- Politics and government; Suffolk (Va.) -- History; Virginia -- History; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1840-1907 and undated, (42 boxes)
  - 1840-1850 Apr.; case of Harriet Whitehead; photographs; information on collection (Box 1)
  - 1850 May-1852 (Box 2)
  - 1853-1855 June (Box 3)
  - 1855 July-1856 (Box 4)
  - 1857 (Box 5)
  - 1858 Jan.-1859 Aug. (Box 6)
  - 1859 Sept.-1862 (Box 7)
  - 1863-Sept. 1866 (Box 8)
  - 1866 Oct-Aug 1867 (Box 9)
  - 1867 Sept.-Feb. 1868 (Box 10)
  - 1868 March-1868 Aug. (Box 11)
  - 1868 Sept.-1869 April (Box 12)
  - 1869 May-1870 Feb. (Box 13)
  - 1870 March-1870 Sept. (Box 14)
  - 1870 Oct.-1871 April (Box 15)
  - 1871 May-Nov. (Box 16)
  - 1871 Dec.-1872 April (Box 17)
  - 1872 May-1872 Oct. (Box 18)
  - 1872 Nov.-1873 March (Box 19)
  - 1873 April-1873 Oct. (Box 20)
  - 1873 Nov.-1874 May (Box 21)
  - 1874 June-1874 Dec. (Box 22)
  - 1875 Jan.-1875 June (Box 23)
  - 1874 July-1876 Jan. (Box 24)
  - 1876 Feb.-1876 Aug. (Box 25)
  - 1876 Sept.-1877 Sept. (Box 26)
  - 1877 Oct.-1878 Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1879-1881 June (Box 28)
  - 1881 July-1883 March (Box 29)
  - 1883 April-1886 June (Box 30)
  - 1885 July-1886 Dec. (Box 31)
  - 1887-1888 Aug. (Box 32)
  - 1888 Sept.-1890 June (Box 33)
  - 1890 July-1891 (Box 34)
  - 1892 Jan.-1893 Dec. (Box 35)
  - 1894 Jan.-1895 June (Box 36)
  - 1895 July-1896 Aug. (Box 37)
  - 1896 Sept.-1897 Dec. (Box 38)
  - 1898 Jan.-1899 Dec. (Box 39)
  - 1900-1901 (Box 40)
  - 1902-1905 May (Box 41)
  - 1905 June-1907 Dec. and undated (Box 42)
- Legal Papers Series, 1680-1907 and undated, (18 boxes)
  - 1680-1842 (Box 43)
  - 1843-1851 (Box 44)
  - 1852-1855 (Box 45)
  - 1856-1858 (Box 46)
  - 1859-1863 (Box 47)
  - 1864-1866 (Box 48)
  - 1867-1868 (Box 49)
  - 1869-1871 Sept. (Box 50)
  - 1871 Oct.-1874 June (Box 51)
  - 1874 July-1877 (Box 52)
  - 1878-1882 (Box 53)
  - 1883-1886 (Box 54)
  - 1887-1892 (Box 55)
  - 1893-1907 (Box 56)
  - Miscellaneous papers and undated items, (4 boxes) (Box 57-60)
- Financial Papers Series, 1814-1909 and undated, (25 boxes)
  - 1814-1840s (Box 61)
  - 1840s, (2 boxes) (Box 62-63)
  - 1850s, (5 boxes) (Box 64-68)
  - 1850s-1860 (Box 69)
  - 1860-1866 (Box 70)
  - 1867-1869, 1860 (Box 71)
  - 1860s, (2 boxes) (Box 72-3)
  - 1860s-1870s (Box 74)
  - 1870s, (5 boxes) (Box 75-79)
  - 1870s-1880s (Box 80)
  - 1880s-1890s (Box 81)
  - 1890s-1900s (Box 82)
  - Undated (Box 83)
  - Undated, also printed material (Box 84)
  - Genealogy, miscellaneous papers, volumes (Box 85)
Partial List of Wills in Collection by Name, County, and Date (mostly copies of original wills)
These can be found in the Legal Papers Series.
Transfer, Katharine, widow of Philemon Haywood, quoting will of Henry Lowe, Sr., 1747 Oct. 13
Extract, William Crawford, 1762 Jan. 27
Extract, George Veale, 1776 Jan. 16
Extract, Samuel Veale, 1793 Mar. 12
Wm. Garrison, Jr., 1776, Accomack Co., Va.
Jonathan Garrison, 1789, Accomack Co., Va.
George Garrison, 1789, Accomack Co., Va.
George Garrison, 1788 Mar.
John Garrison, 1795, Accomack Co., Va.
Rachel Garrison, 1801, Accomack Co., Va.
Extract, George Hall, 1823 May 7
Extract, William Deams, 1825
Thomas Radwell, 1819 Jan. 2, Mansemone [Nansemond?] Co., Va.
John Glazebrook, 1824 July 13, Hanover Co. Va.
Legal document on this will, 1847 Oct.
Sarah Shivers, 1827 Nov. 28, Isle of Wight Co. Va.
Extract, Alfred Ames, 1830 Jan. 19
Extract, Josiah Riddick, 1838 Sept. 16, Nansemond Co., Va.
Extract, John Harrell, 1840 Mar. 2
Joseph Wright, 1840 May 29, Nansemond Co., Va.
Extract, William Addison, 1841 Mar. 21
William Murphrey, Nansemond Co., 1841 July 31
James Parker, 1843 Jan. 23, Nansemond Co.
Joseph Corbell, 1809 May 19
Joseph Vaughan, 1855 Aug. 3, Nansemond Co.
Thomas Tartt, 1856 Feb. 11, Norfolk Co.
Robert H. Tatem, 1856 May 21, Norfolk Co.
William Green, 1857 Jan. 5, Isle of Wight Co.
Exum Jenkins 1857 Nov. 20, Nansemond Co.
Richard Riddick, n.d., Beaufort Co., revoked in favor of later will (1857 Nov. 13?), original
Richard Riddick, 1857 Dec. 13, Beaufort Co., original
John Gray, 1858 May 25, original
Excerpts, Theoderick Robertson, 1853 July 21
Drewry Waller, 1859 May 28, Southhampton Co.
Extract, Mrs. Bunch, 1861 Aug. 12
James Majitt, 1861 Apr. 4, Va.
Lumuel Vaughan, 1862 Nov. 10, Hanover Co.; codicil, 4 June 1864
Archie C. Godwin, 1863 June 13, N.C., original
Thomas Hall, 1863 Nov. 2, Isle of Wight
William H. Goodwin, 1864 Aug. 31, Nansemond Co.
Nancy Barrett, 1855 Nov. 17, Isle of Wight, original
William H. Summerell, 1864 Nov. 14, Southampton
Ro. Laurence, 1865 Oct. 28, Nansemond
Jesse Perry, 1863 Aug 8, Nansemond